consider the graphs of two different
sequences first I've graphed a random a
n that I made up and then I went and
graphed the absolute value of that same
sequence and then the top sequence a
there were some positive and negative
terms when I take the absolute value it
takes all of those negatives and makes
them all positives now this is a
sequence and in both of these sequences
at least visually it appears that the
limits going to be 0 but just because
the limit of the terms goes to 0 doesn't
say anything about what the series does
so let's investigate that let's compare
the series that adds up the a n to the
series that adds up the absolute value
of the a n now because that program is
saying I happen to know what this series
is this is the series minus 1 to the n
minus 1 all divided by square root of n
so the absolute value the effect it has
is just takes all that minus 1 stuff and
gets rid of it it just all turns it into
plus 1 now these two sequences are ones
that we can do by previous methods we've
seen the top one it's an alternating
thing with the minus 1 to the n minus 1
and then it multiplies it by 1 over
spurred n which is a positive decreasing
sequence with limit 0 it satisfies all
conditions of the alternating series
test so that top one indeed converges by
the alternating series test as for the
bottom one this is AP test it's AP with
N equal to 1/2 and so this is a p-series
that diverges so the lesson here is that
taking absolute values of the terms
makes a big deal in this example it
converts it from a convergent to a
divergent series no why might that be
the case if you think about the one with
positives and negatives when you take a
positive term and you add it to a
negative term it cancels maybe not
entirely all the way but the combination
of positives and negatives they don't
add up as much as only adding positives
or alternatively only adding negatives
together so when you take the absolute
value you get rid of any form of
internal cancellation that you have so
it would make sense that the absolute
value one would be the larger that it
might diverge even though the one with
the minus signs that converged and
indeed this is generally the case
so if here
that we have is that if the sum of the
absolute value of the ANS converges then
the original series with just the end
that converges as well it says that you
put this absolute value around it you
have a stronger condition so when you
know it converges with the absolutes
there then it converges without them
deep a little bit of terminology here
we'll say that absolute convergence that
expression is what we mean when we take
the sum of the absolute value of a ends
so another way to say this is that if it
converges absolutely then it converges
in the normal sense but the other
direction is not true if something
converges like in the example we saw
before that converged by the alternating
series test it does not necessarily
converge absolutely it might but it
might not and in that scenario where it
doesn't we call this conditional
convergence so conditional convergence
is where the original series converges
but does not converge absolutely it
doesn't converge when you wrap it in
absolute value signs indeed this example
that we started the video with this
minus 1 to the n minus 1 over root n
that was a conditionally convergent
series it converged but it didn't
converge absolutely so these are just a
couple of pieces of terminology that are
going to be very important for our next
test the ratio test and the root test